all right you guys see the slides I assume
Alfredo I can't see you I can't see anyone else so yes all right
yeah it's all good you can also make signs I can see you
okay um so um we're going to talk about still talk
about energy-based models and mostly in the context of
self supervised or unsupervised learning continuing
where we left off last time so let me start with a little bit of
reminder of where we where we left last time
we talked about self supervised learning as the idea of
basically trying to predict everything from everything else
pretending that a part of the input is not visible to the system and another
part is visible and we train the system to predict the
non-visible part from the visible part and of course it could be it could be
anything could be part of a video or it could be
something else there is a special case where uh
we don't assume that anything is visible at any time and so we're just asking the
system to just predict uh out of the blue without any input
so we talked about this the approach of energy-based models
which consist in essentially basically having an implicit function
that captures the dependency between x and y
or in the case where you don't have an x is the dependency between the various
components of y and the reason why we need a implicit
function is that for a particular value of x there could
be multiple values of y that are that are possible
and so if we had a direct prediction from x to y we could only make one
prediction and using an implicit function we can make multiple
predictions implicitly by basically having a function that gives
lower energy for multiple values of y for a given value of x
and that's a little bit what's uh represented on the on the left with
uh essentially you can think of this as some sort of
landscape mountainous landscape where the data points
are in the valleys and everything else at size the manifold of data is
uh has higher energy so inference in this context proceeds by
basically finding a y or a set of y's that
minimize F of x y for a given x so this is not learning yet learning
consists in shaping F but this we're just talking about
inference so it's very important to be able to make the difference between
the inference process of minimizing the energy function to
find y and then the learning process which is
minimizing a loss function not the energy function
with respect to the parameters of the energy function okay the two different
things and in the case of
the unconditional case you don't have an x and so you're only capturing the
mutual dependencies between y's we talked about latent variable models
and the reason why we talk about latent variable models is that it's a
particular way of representing uh or building the architecture of the
energy function in such a way that it can have a
multiple y for a given x so essentially a latent variable is an
extra variable z that nobody gives you the value of but
the first thing you do when you see a z is that you minimize your energy
function with respect to that z and that gives you now an energy
function that does not depend on z anymore
okay or if you want to do uh inference with a model with latent
variable I give you an x and you find the combination of y and z
that minimize the energy and then you give me y
that's the that's the inference process these two ways to do
inference with respect to a variable that you don't observe uh one is to just
minimize over it as I just indicated and the other one is to marginalize over
it if you are a probabilist but even in other cases
and there is a simple formula to kind of go from one to the other
which is basically a log sum exponential over all possible values of z and this
may be intractable so we don't do this very
often okay so training an energy based model
consists in parameterizing the energy function
and collecting of course a bunch of training samples a bunch of x and y's
in the conditional case or just a bunch of y's in a
unconditional case and then it consists in shaping the energy function so that
you give low energy to good combinations of x and y's and higher energy to buy
combinations of x and y so for a given observed x
you try to make F of y for the corresponding y that corresponds to
x as low as possible but then you also need to make the
energy F of x and y larger for all other values of y all
other possible values of y and it's probably a good idea to keep
this energy function smooth if you are in a continuous space if y is a
continuous variable because I'll make inference easier
subsequently you'll be able to use gradient descent
based methods to do inference or maybe other methods
so there's two classes of learning algorithms as we talked about last time
the first class is contrastive methods which consist in basically pushing down
on the energy of training samples so you
get a training sample x[i] y[i] uh you plug it into your energy
function and then you tune the parameters of the
energy function so that that energy goes down
and you can do this uh with uh you know with backdrop if
if your energy function is some sort of neural net with other things in it as
long as as it's a differentiable function you
can you can do that but then uh what you have to do as well
is pick other points that are outside the
manifold of data and then push their energy up
so that the energy gets takes the right shape okay
so those are contrastive methods and then there's architectural methods and
the architectural methods basically consist in building F of x y
in such a way that the volume of space that can take low
energy is limited perhaps minimized in some way
and so if you push down on the energy of certain points automatically the rest
will be up because we go up because the
volume of stuff that can take low energy is
is limited and I've made a list here uh so this is
an important slide which you you saw last time
and there's a list of various methods that you may have heard of
some of which are contrastive some of which are architectural I must say that
those two classes of methods are not necessarily incompatible with each other
you can very well use a combination of the two
but most methods only use one so things like maximum likelihood if your
probability consists in pushing down on the energy of data
points and then pushing up every everywhere else
for every other value of y in proportion to how low the energy is so you push up
harder if the energy is lower so that in the end you get kind of the
the right shape maximum likelihood incidentally only cares about
differences of energy it doesn't doesn't care about absolute values of
energies um which is an important point and then
there are other methods like contrastive divergence
uh metric learning ratio matching noise contrastive estimation minimum
probability flow things like that which and uh generative
average several networks that also are based on the idea of
pushing up on the energy of data points outside the data manifold
then there are similar methods uh um denoising autoencoders that we will
talk about in just a minute and uh as we saw last time they've been
extremely successful in the context of natural language processing uh systems
like BERT for example basically are denoising autoencoder of
a particular kind and then there are architectural methods
and last time we talked a little bit about PCA and k-means
um but they we're going to talk about a few more
today particularly sparse coding and something called LISTA
and I'm not going to talk about the remaining ones
so this is a rehash again of something that we talked about last
last week which is a very simple latent variable model for
unsupervised learning k-means which I'm sure you all you've all heard about
there the energy function is simply the square reconstruction error between the
data vector and the product of a prototype matrix
times a latent variable vector and that latent
variable vector is constrained to be a one-hot vector so in other words it
selects one of the columns of w when you
multiply W by by it and so what you get in the end
is the uh the square distance between the
data vector and the uh column of W that is closest to it
uh once you do the minimization with respect to z which means you know
looking for which column W is closest to y so that's the energy
function that's the inference algorithm looking for the closest prototype and uh
the energy function of course is zero wherever there is a prototype
and grows quadratically as you move away from the prototype
until you get closer to another prototype in which case the energy
again goes down as you get closer to the second prototype
so if you train k-means on a data set where the training samples are generated
by uh peeking around this little uh spiral
here shown at the bottom um what you'll you you with kaggle 20 in
that case you get those uh little dark areas which indicate the
the minima of the energy function and there is a
ridge in the middle um where you know the sort of energy uh
it's like um you know the energy kind of goes down on
both sides it's like a ridge um but here is uh a method that's become
very popular over the last few months and it's very recent
the the first papers on this actually go back a long time there are some of my
papers from the early 90s and from the the mid-2000s um and they were called
siamese networks or metric learning at the time
and the idea is to build a uh a uh sort of energy-based model if you want
by uh having two copies of the same network or
two different networks but very often these two copies of the same network
and you feed uh x to the first network and y to the second network
you have them compute some feature vector on the output h and h prime
and then you compare those two feature vectors with some
some methods some some way of computing a similarity or dissimilarity
between vectors it could be a dot product could be a cosine
a similarity it could be something of that type
and what you do is uh to train the system is that
you you train it with a data point basically is a pair
of x and y um so you indicate the location of the the
data manifold to the system by basically telling it
here is a here is a sample tell me is a sample x
give me another sample that basically has
the same content as x but it's different and of course you're never going to ask
the system to give you that sample you're going to generate
those samples and train the system with it so
there are there are two pairs uh positive pairs so pairs are compatible
with each other which is a whole idea of energy based models
and a compatible pair is or a positive pair if you want
is consist of x being an image and y being a transformation of this image
that basically does not change its content so it's still the same content
of the image if you want so you want basically uh representations
extracted by those two networks to be very similar
because those images are similar and that's exactly what you're gonna do
you're gonna feed those two images to those two those two networks
and you're gonna have a loss function that that says minimize the energy which
means minimize the distance or similarity measure between h and h prime
between the outputs of the two networks um so that's the positive part so that's
a way to kind of lower the energy for for training samples
okay and then you have to generate random
uh negative samples and the way you generate them is by
basically picking again a sample for x and then picking another image that you
know is different that has nothing to do with
x, it's incompatible with it if you want it's very different
and now what you do is you feed those two images to those two networks
and you try to push h and h prime away from each other
so basically you're trying to make the the similarity matrix c of h and h prime
large for those two samples okay
and the objective function here is going to take into account
uh uh the the object the the energy function for similar part
pairs and the energy function for dissimilar pairs
is going to push down on the energy function for similar pairs push up on
the energy function for dissimilar pairs okay um
so there's been a number of uh uh so paper
you know people have used metric learning for various things for a long
time for uh image search for example uh for
uh feature recognition for for things like that
but it's only in the last few months that there's been
a couple of works that have shown they can use those methods to
learn good features for object recognition
and those are really the first papers that produce features
in a unsupervised or self-supervised way that produce features that can rival the
features that are obtained through supervised learning
so the three papers in question are PIRL which means protecting
representation learning by Isha Misra and
Lawrence van der Maaten at facebook in new york another one called
Moco by KamingHe and his collaborators at facebook in Menlo park
and the third one which appeared more recently is called SimCLR
by a group from google Chen et al. and the last author being
Jeffery Hinton so the um
there's been other work uh using those kind of methods uh, I think there was a
question, perhaps it wasn't a question, it was actually my
phone waking up because I said Google and oh I see okay and and through
features that's something we'll talk we'll talk about later which is
a little a little similar okay so these are examples of results
that are obtained with MoCo and uh they essentially show that even with
a very large model you can which is basically a version of resnet50
that you train using this code some contrasting method
uh you get sort of decent performance this is I believe uh
uh top five performance on uh on imagenet
PIRL actually works uh quite a bit better than than MoCo this is
uh top one accuracy this time um with uh uh networks of this size so
sizes, so here the there's several scenarios the the main scenario is
you take all of your imagenet you uh you take a sample from imagenet
distort it and that gives you a positive pair uh run it through
your two networks and train the the network to
produce similar outputs basically the two networks are identical
actually for both MoCo and PIRL it's the same its net and then
take dissimilar pairs and push the outputs away from each other using a
particular cost function that we'll see in a minute
and then you have to do this many many times and you have to be smart about
how you cache the negative samples because
most samples are already very different by the time they they get to the output
to the network so you basically have to be smart about how
you kind of pick the the good negatives so the type of uh objective function
that is used by by PIRL is called the noise
contrastive estimation and that goes back to kind of
previous papers it's not it's not their uh invention
where the the similarity metric is this uh is the cosine similarity
measure between the outputs of the commercial nets
and and then what you compute is this uh basically the softmax-like
function which computes the exponential of the similarity metric
of two outputs for similar pairs and then divides by
the sum of the similarity metric exponentiated for similar pairs and the
sum of dissimilar pairs so you have a batch where you have one similar pair
and a bunch of dissimilar pairs and you compute this kind of softmax
thing and if you minimize its softmax cost function is going to push the
similarity similarity metric of similar pair to be
as large as possible and the the similarity metric the cosine
similarity of dissimilar pair to be basically as small as possible. I had
this question that why are we separately using an LNCE
function whereas we could have probably directly
computed laws using the the h v(I) v(I transformed) uh
probability that we have by taking the negative log of that probability
so like what benefit would LNCE provide
using uh like not directly taking the negative log of the
probability that we have from h? Well that's a good question um it's not
entirely clear to me why uh I think uh what what what happened
there is that people tried lots and lots of different
things and this is what ended up working best
there is uh in the the Hinton paper there's kind of a similar thing where
they tried different types of uh objective function
and found that something like NCE actually works quite well
so it's an empirical question and I I don't have a good tuition for why
you need this uh this term uh in addition to the just the
denominator uh in h um I hope this answers your question
although sorry I don't have any answer for it
why do you use cosines similarity instead of l2 norm
instead of l2 norm or instead of okay it's because
you it's because you want to normalize it's very easy to make two vectors
similar by making them very short or to make two vectors very
dissimilar but making them very long okay so by doing cosine similarity
you're basically normalizing right you're computing a dot product but
you're normalizing this dot product and so you make the measure independent
of the length of the of the vectors and so it uh it forces
the system to kind of find a good good solution to the problem without
just without cheating by just making the uh you know vectors either short or or
large it it also removes a an instability that
they could be in the system the the design of those contrasting
functions is actually quite uh quite a bit of a black heart
okay so what they actually do in PIRL is that they um
they they don't use directly the uh the output of the of the convnet for the
for the objective function they they have different heads
so basically the the convnet has different set of heads f and g
which are different for the two networks and
that's what they use in the context of this contractive learning and then there
is you know another head that they use for
the the ultimate task of of classification
so those f and g functions are you can think of as sort of extra
layers that are kind of uh on top of the network that
are different for the two the two for the two networks all right so these are
the these are the results that are produced
by uh by PIRL and uh you can get so this is this
particular experiment is one in which you pre-trained the the system using
perl on the imagenet training set and then what you do is uh you
you you retrain you fine tune the system using either one percent of the labeled
samples or ten percent of the label samples and you you measure the
performance top five accuracy or top one accuracy
so this paper appeared in uh in January on archive
um and then just a few weeks ago uh this paper appeared called SimCLR
by Chen et al. which is a team from google and they
have a very sophisticated corruption or data augmentation method to generate
similar pairs and they train uh for a very very long
time on a lot of TPUs and they get really interestingly good
results so much better than either PIRL or MoCo
using very large models and they can reach you know more than 75
percent correct top one on imagenet by just
pre-training in self supervised fashion and then kind
of fine tuning with only one percent of the
other samples yeah so this is uh in fact the previous slide is a
different scenario uh where you only train a linear
classifier on top of the on top of the network the this is the
scenario where you train with either one percent or ten percent of uh labeled
samples and uh you get uh eighty-five percent
the top five with one percent of the labels which is uh
you know pretty pretty amazing results to some extent I think
this shows the limits of contrasting methods because the amount of
computation and training that is required for this is absolutely gigantic
it's it's really enormous so here is a scenario where you
just train a linear classifier on top so you you freeze the features
uh produced by the system that has been uh pre-trained using uh
self-supervised learning and then you just train a linear classifier on top
and you measure the performance of total point of top five
on the full image net having trained supervisor on the full imagenet
and again the numbers are really impressive
but again I think it shows the limit of contracting methods here is the
the main issue with contrasting methods is that there are many many many
locations in a high dimensional space where you
need to push up the energy to make sure that it's actually higher
uh everywhere than on the data manifold
and so as you increase the dimension of the representation
you need more and more negative samples to make sure that the energy is higher
uh where it needs to be higher. Okay so let's talk about another
another crop of uh of contrasting methods called denoising auto-encoder and
that's become really uh kind of important over the
last uh year and a half or so for for natural
language processing uh so the idea of denoising auto encoder
is that you take a y and the way you generate x is by
corrupting y so this sounds a little bit like the opposite of what we were just
doing with contrastive methods but
basically you take a clean image why you corrupt it in some way by removing a
piece of it for example or you take a piece of text and you
remove some of the words or you mask a piece of it so a special case is the
masked auto encoder where the corruption consists in masking a subset
of the input and then you run this through an auto
encoder which is uh you know essentially a an encoder or
called a predictor here a decoder and you know perhaps uh
you know final layers that that you know may have uh
uh softmax in the context of text or not if you know nothing of its
images and then you compute you compare the predicted output
uh y bar with the uh with the observed data
y and so what's the what's the principle
of this the principle of this is that is is the following
and uh you can thank Alfredo for those beautiful pictures
basically, yeah we saw this in class last Tuesday
that's right so uh this is basically just a reminder
you take a data point you so which is one of those
pink points right and you corrupt it so you get one of those
brown points and then you train the uh auto encoder to
from the brown point to produce the pink points
the the original pink point what does that mean that means that
now the energy function which is the reconstruction error is going to be
equal to the difference between the original
point the pink point the distance the square distance
if C is the euclidean square euclidean distance
so c yybar is going to be the if you think it's properly trained
is going to be the the distance between the corrupted point
uh x uh the the brown point and the and the pink point you started from y
okay so basically it basically it basically
trains the the system to produce an energy function that grows
quadratically as you move away from the data manifold okay
um and so it's an example of a contrastive method because you push up
on the energy of points that are outside the data manifold essentially you tell
them your energy should be the square
distance to the data manifold or at least to the point that was used
before you know to through corruption
but the problem with it is that again in a high dimensional continuous space
there is many many many ways you can corrupt
a piece of data and uh it's not entirely clear that you're going to be able to
kind of shape the energy function the proper way by just pushing up on lots of
different locations it works in text because text is
discrete it doesn't work so well in images people
have used this in the context of imaging painting for example so the corruption
consists of masking a piece of the image and then training a
system to reconstruct it and the reason why it doesn't work is
because uh people tend to train the system without latent variables and
in my little diagram here there is a latente variable but uh
in fact in uh versions of this that are used
for uh in the context of images there is no real latent variable and it's very
difficult for the system to just dream up
a single solution to the in painting problem here it's a
it's a multimodal [Music]
manifold I mean it's a it's a manifold it's probably not
just a single point there's many ways to complete the image here uh by
filling in the the the the masked uh part
and so uh without latent variable the system produces blurry predictions and
doesn't learn particularly good features. Is the multi-modal part also the reason
why we had that internal purple area in the spiral because each
of those points have two predictions right in between the two branches of the
spiral? right so this is the additional problem
that uh if you don't uh if you're not careful the you know
points that are in the middle that you know that that could be the
result of a corruption of uh uh one uh pink point on one side of the
manifold or a pink point on another side of the manifold
the those points right in the middle don't know where to go because half the
time they're trained to go to uh one part of the manifold the other
half of the time they're trying to go to the other part of the manifold
and so uh that might create kind of flat spots in the energy function that uh are
not good so there you know there are ways to alleviate this but they're not
kind of completely uh worked out unless you use latent
variable models. okay other contrasting methods this is
just in passing for for your own uh interest there are
things like contrastive divergence um and and others which I'm not going to
talk about but contrastive divergence is is a very simple idea you pick a
training sample you lower the energy at that point of
course and then from that sample you using some sort of gradient-based
process you move down the energy surface with noise so
start from the sample and figure out how do I change my sample how do I change my
y in such a way that my
current energy based model produces a lower energy than the one I just
i just measured for that sample okay so basically you're trying to find
another point in input space that has lower energy than
the training point you just fed it okay so you can think of this as
kind of a smart way of corrupting a training sample smart
because you you don't randomly uh uh
corrupt it you corrupt it by uh basically modifying it to find a point
in space that your model already gives low energy to so it would
be a point that you would want to push up because
your model gives low energy to it and you don't want it to have low energy so
you push it up and I'm gonna uh professor have people try tried uh
contrastive methods with the this image inpainting method and
how would one do that does that really work if they if you do that together
so inpainting is a contrastive method right you you take an image
you corrupt it by uh blocking some piece of it
and then you train uh a neural net uh basically an autoencoder to generate the
the full image and then you compare this reconstruction
of the full image with the original uncorrupted image and that's your energy
function okay so it is it is a contrasting method
right so if we if we use like uh the NCE loss with this uh inpainting loss
uh does that uh like is that useful uh you can really use NCE loss because
NCE kind of relies on the fact that you you have sort of a finite number of
negative samples okay here you sort of artificially generate
negative samples and so uh it's really a completely
different scenario i don't think you would
you could use uh something similar to NCE
or at least not in a meaningful way okay so this is why space
okay y one y two and let's say your your data manifold
is something like this um but let's say your energy function
currently is something like this so here I'm drawing
the region of low energy and I'm drawing the lines of
equal cost okay so the energy looks nice at the bottom left right you have data
points here that your model gives low energy to but
then your model is not good because uh at the bottom right it gives low
energy to regions that have no data and then at the
at the top you have data points that that your model gives high energy
to okay so here's how contrasty divergence would work
you take a sample a training sample it tells this guy and by gradient
descent you go down the energy surface
to a point that has low energy okay now this was a training sample y
the one you obtain now is a contrastive sample y bar
and what you do now is you change the parameters of your energy function
so that you make the energy of y smaller and the energy of y bar larger
okay using some kind of loss function that
you know pushes down on one pushes up on the other which loss function you use
is a material you just need one that will do the right thing
okay so what I've described here is kind of a deterministic version of
uh contrasting divergence but in fact contrasted divergence is kind of a
probabilistic version of this where what you do is you you do this
sort of gradient based descent i mean this sort of
search for a low energy point but you do it with some level of random
randomness some noise in it so one way to do this in a continuous
space like like this one is that you give a random kick
you you think of your data point here as a sort of a marble
that is going to go down the energy surface you give it a random kick in
in some random direction say this and then you let the the system kind of
follow the gradient and you stop when you're tired you don't
wait for it to kind of go down all the way you just stop when
you're tired and then there is a rule to select whether you keep the point or not
um and that's your that's your y bar why is the kick necessary okay so the
kick is necessary so that you can go over energy barriers that would be
between you and the the lowest energy uh
uh areas okay that's why you need the the kick now uh if you have
uh a space a y space that is not continuous but is discrete
uh you can still kind of do this energy minimization by basically doing
something called simulated annealing so essentially uh
if y is discrete variable you kind of perturb it randomly
if the energy you get by this perturbation is lower then you keep it
if it's higher then you keep it with some probability
and then you keep doing this and eventually the energy will go down so
this is a non-gradient-based optimization algorithm or gradient-free
optimization algorithm if you want which you kind of have to resort to when
the space is discrete and you can't use gradient information
this technique I just described of kicking a
a marble and sort of simulating it rolling down the
energy it's called Hamiltonian monte carlo hnc
and you might you might see this in other in other contexts
so that's another way of generating negative samples yes Hamiltonian monte
carlo some people call this hybrid monte carlo
sometimes so some of you may have heard of
something called restricted boltzmann machine and restricted
boltzmann machine is an energy based model in which the energy
is very simple um it's written at the bottom here
the energy of y and z so y is basically an input data vector and z
is uh it's a related variable the energy function is minus
z transpose w y where y where where w is a matrix uh not necessarily square
because z and y may have different uh uh dimensions
and uh generally z and y are both binary variables
and so I mean the binary vectors so the components are binary variables
and they were kind of somewhat popular in the mid-2000s but you know I'm not
spending much time on it here because uh um the the they've kind of fallen out of
favor a little bit they're not they're not that popular but just so
that gives you some reference of what uh what this means um there's
of refinements of contrastive divergence one of them is called persistent
contrastive divergence and it consists in using a bunch of
particles um and you can remember the position so
they have sort of permanent uh persistent positions if you want
uh so you throw a bunch of uh marbles in your
energy landscape and you keep making you keep making them roll down maybe
with a little bit of noise or or kicks and then you keep their
position so you don't change the the the position of the marble according
to new samples new training samples you just keep the marbles where they are
and eventually they'll find low energy places in your
in your energy surface and will cause them to be pushed up
because because that's what happens during
during training but this doesn't scale very well so
things like RBMs you know become very very expensive to to train
within in high dimension okay so now for
regularized latent-variable energy based model which
is my current favorite type of model so we we talked about the idea of
building a predictive model by having a latent variable right so you have
the observed variable x you run it to a predictor it extracts some
representation of the observed variables and then that
goes into a decoder that produces the prediction but if you want your decoder
to be able to make multiple predictions
then you feed it with a latent variable and as you vary
the value of this latent variable the prediction will vary over a set
okay over hopefully the manifold of data of uh
in the space of y that are compatible with x
so this architecture here is here the the formula for the energy can be
written as as on the left here uh c of y
and uh you know c is a cost function that compares these two argument so you
compare y the data vector with the result of applying the decoder to the
output of the predictor that takes into account x
and the decoder also takes into account z
so here is the problem with this if z is too powerful in other words if z has
too much capacity then they're always going to be a z that
is going to produce a y bar that's going to be exactly equal to y
so remember the uh the inference algorithm here is that you give an x and
a y and then you find a z that minimizes c
of y y bar right that's how you
do inference of the latent variable in an energy-based model right
given an x and y find the z that minimizes the energy
so if z for example has the same dimension as y
and the decoder is powerful enough to represent the identity function
then for any y there's always going to be a z that produces y bar that's
exactly equal to y okay and if the decoder is the identity
function which ignores h see an identity function
from z to to uh to y to y bar then you just set
z equal to y and the energy is zero and that would be a terrible energy
based model because it would not give high energy to stuff
outside the manifold of data it gives low energy to everything
okay it gives zero energy to everything so the way to prevent the system from
giving low energy to points outside the manifold of data
is to limit the information capacity of the
latent variable z to be more precise if z can only take
let's say 10 different values what that means is so you constrain z to
only take ten possible different values let's say you make z a
a one hot vector of dimension ten like in k-means okay then there's only
going to be 10 points in y space that will have zero energy because
either y is equal to one of the y bars that is produced from one of those ten
z's or it's not if it is then the energy is
zero if it's not the energy is gonna have to be larger than zero in
fact it's going to grow quadratically as you move away from
uh from that z and that's exactly the idea of k-means
okay but what if you find other ways to limit the information
content of z so this seems like a kind of a small
technical sub problem but in my opinion the
question of how you limit the information content of a latent variable
in a model of this type is the most important question in AI
today okay and I'm not kidding
I think the the main problem we're facing is is how to do
self-supervised learning uh properly and contrastive methods have shown their
limits and so we have to find alternatives and alternatives are
uh regularized latent-variable models there might be other ideas that nobody has had
so far but these are the only two that I know
of and then the main technical issue that we need to solve is
how do we limit the information content of the latent variable so that we limit
the volume of y space that can take low energy
and therefore we automatically make the energy outside the
the the manifold of data where we train the system to have low energy
we automatically make the energy outside uh higher
so I'm going to go through a few examples of systems that actually work
that uh and things that people have done for
you know uh 20 years in some cases um and so so that's the idea here
you you um or one of the ideas you add a regularizer
in the energy and this regularizer takes low value
on a kind of small part of the space of z
and so the system will preferentially choose values of z
that are within this sort of restricted set where R takes a small value
and if z needs to go outside of that set to do a
good reconstruction you're paying a price for it in terms of
energy okay so
the the the volume of uh of z space that is determined by R basically limits
the volume of uh space of y that can take low energy
and the tradeoff is controlled by uh basically a coefficient lambda that you
can uh adjust to uh you know make the
the volume of uh y space that take low energy as uh as small as possible or
or not that small so here are a few examples of R(z) of r
of r of z and some of them are kind of
useful because they're differentiable with respect to z and some of them are
not so useful because they're not differentiable so you have to look for
kind of you know do a discrete search so one is the effective dimension of
z so what you can do is you can decide that z a priori has
three dimension four dimension five dimension six dimension you train your
model for various dimensions of z and there is one set of dimensions for
which you know one dimension for which the prediction would be good but at the
same time uh the dimension of z would be minimized
and what you will have found is basically the lowest uh embedding
dimension of your of your space so imagine for example that uh your data
set consists of lots and lots of pictures of
someone making faces in front of a camera
we know that the effective dimension of the manifold of all the faces of a
person is something like 60 at least less than
100 because it's bounded above by the number of muscles in your face
and so there has to be a a z of dimension
50 or 60 or something like that such that when you run it through a
convolutional net you will generate all possible uh instances of
uh of the the face of that person okay that's the the face manifold for
that person if you want um so what you can do is this a really
super expensive method of kind of trying all different
different dimensions of z uh one way to formulate this
mathematically is uh to minimize the L0 norm of z
so uh it's actually a slightly different thing so
what you um what what you can do is you choose a z that's relatively high
dimension but for any given sample you minimize
the number of components of z that are non-zero okay that's called the
l0 norm it's just the account of the number of components that are non-zero
and it's very difficult to uh minimize that uh that norm because it's
not differentiable it's very discrete so what people use is they use a convex
relaxation of that norm called and it's the l1 norm so the l1 norm is
the sum of the absolute values or the
components of z and that's what you use for r and z the
sum of the absolute values of the components of z
when you add this to your energy function
what the system is trying to do is find a z
that reconstructs the the y because it needs to minimize c of y and y bar
but also tries to minimize the number of its components that are non-zero because
that's the best way to minimize the l1 norm
okay and that's called sparse coding and it works
really well and I'm going to show you some examples of this
before I go there I just want to mention that and we'll talk about this a little
more and it's the idea that adding noise to z
will also limit the information content of z I'll come
back to this in a minute okay so here is the uh idea of
of sparse coding so sparse coding is an unconditional version
of energy-based model so there's no x there's only a y
and a z and the energy function is y minus Wz where W is a so-called
dictionary matrix very similar to the prototype matrix in
k-means z is a vector generally the dimension of
z is larger than y and so you measure the squared distance
euclidean distance between y and Wz so basically your decoder here is
linear it's just a matrix and then you add a term lambda times the
l1 norm of z which is represented by those two bars
and that's the energy function for sparse coding okay and you can think of
it as a special case of the the system I I showed the
architecture i showed previously uh except it's not um conditional
there's no x now what does this do um
um so Alfredo will tell you that the picture I'm showing here on the left
uh is inappropriate because it's actually generated with a slightly
different model um but it's uh a good sort of pictorial
representation of what uh what sparse coding attempts to do
which is to approximate the manifold of data
by a piecewise linear approximation essentially
so imagine that you have this w matrix okay and someone
has given it to you or you've learned it in some way
now if you decide a priori that a certain
number of components of z are non-zero okay most of the components of z are
zero just a small number of components with z are nonzero
and you vary the value of those components
you know within some range the set of vectors that you're going to generate
the set of y bars that you're going to generate
are going to be the y bars that are in the linear subspace spanned by the
corresponding columns of the W matrix okay for every value of the z
coefficients that are nonzero you basically compute a linear
combination of the corresponding columns of W
and so you're basically moving along a low dimensional
linear subspace of of y space so y bar is going to be basically along
a low dimensional space a low dimensional linear subspace
the dimension of that space will be the number of non-zero components of z
okay so for one particular y when you find the z
that minimizes the the energy a number of components are
going to be nonzero and as you move y slowly those nonzero
components are going to change value but you're going to stay on the
same linear subspace until y change changes
too much and then all of a sudden you need a
different set of non-zero z to do a the best reconstruction and now
you're switching to a different plane okay because a different set of z now of
z components become non-zero um and so now you you move y again and
again the coefficients in z keep changing values except for the ones
that are zero that stay zero and all of a sudden it switches again it
goes to another one so it's it's kind of well symbolized by
the the picture on the left where you see that the
manifold of data is approximated by basically a bunch of
uh linear subspace in in this case lines um the reason why it's difficult to
represent the actual sparse coding uh in 2d is because it's going to
degenerate in 2d so so one question is how do we train a
system like this so to train a system like this
we actually uh our loss function is just going to be the average
uh energy that our model gives to our training samples
so the loss function is just the average energy basically the average f
and remember f of y is equal to uh the minimum over z of E of y and z
okay so we're going to take the average of f over all our training samples
and minimize that average with respect to the parameters
of the model and those parameters are the coefficients in the w matrix
again it's called the dictionary matrix so how do we do this we take a sample y
we find the z that minimizes the energy okay the sum of the two terms that you
see here and then we we take one step of gradient
descent in W so we compute the gradient of the
energy with respect to w which is very simple because it's a quadratic function
of W and we take one step of uh of stochastic
gradient basically right and now we take the next y and do it
again minimize with respect to z and then for that value of z compute the
gradient with respect to w and take one step in the negative gradient
and you keep doing this now if you just do this it doesn't work
it doesn't work because the result is that W
keeps will keep getting bigger and bigger and z will keep getting smaller
and smaller but the problem will not actually the
system will not actually solve the problem
so what you need to do is normalize the W matrix so that it cannot grow
indefinitely and allow z to shrink correspondingly
and the way to do this is that you basically after
every update of the W matrix you normalize the sum of the squares
of the the terms in a column of in each column of W
right so normalize the columns of W after each update
and that will prevent the terms in W from blowing up and the terms in z from
shrinking and it will force the system to actually
find a reasonable matrix W and not get away with just making z
shorter okay so that's sparse coding this was uh
the learning algorithm for this was invented by
two computational neural scientists Bruno Olshausen and David Field in 1997
and so that goes back a long time okay so here is the problem with sparse
coding the inference algorithm is kind of
expensive you oops what you have to do is um
you know for for a given y is to kind of minimize the sum of those two terms one
of which is l two the other one is at one
there's a very large number of papers in applied mathematics
that uh explain how to do this efficiently
in particular one algorithm to do to do to do so is called ISTA that means
iterative shrinkage and thresholding algorithm
and I'm going to tell you what ISTA is in just a minute
but it basically consists in uh basically alternating uh a sort of
minimization with a sp of z with respect to z of the first term
and then the second term alternately so here's the kind of abstract form of the
of the ISTA algorithm there's a fast version of it called
called FISTA and here it is at the um at the bottom
um actually I'm realizing that I'm missing the reference for the ISTA
algorithm this is not any of the references i'm showing here
um first author is Deboulid d-e-b-o-u-l-i-d
anyway so here is the algorithm you start with z equals zero
and then you apply uh this iteration here which is the
the second last formula so in the bracket the
the thing that's in the bracket is basically a gradient step in the squared
error the square reconstruction error so if you compute the gradient or the
square reconstruction error and and you do a gradient step you you
basically get this this formula where one over L is the is
the is the the gradient uh step size
okay um so we basically update z with the
negative gradient of the square reconstruction error
and then the next operation you do is a shrinkage operation so you take
every component of the resulting z vector
and you shrink all of them to towards zero so you basically subtract
if the component of z is positive you subtract a constant to it
from it and if it's negative you add a cons the same constant
to it but but if you get too close to zero you just
click at zero okay so basically it's a it's a function that um you know
is flat around zero and then uh grows like the identity function above a
certain threshold and uh and below a certain threshold
okay it shrinks towards zero if you keep iterating this algorithm for
proper values of L and lambda the
z vector will converge to the solution of the
energy minimization problem which is the minimum of this
energy here e of y z with respect to z okay and that suggests uh so
keep this in mind now here is here is an issue this algorithm is
kind of expensive uh if you want to run this
over uh an image or over you know all patches of an image or something like
this you're not going to be able to do this
in real time on large images and so here is an idea and the idea is
to basically train a neural net to predict
what the solution of the energy minimization problem is
okay so you see the diagram here on the right
where um we train an encoder that takes the the y value for now you
can ignore the the piece that depends on x right you
have x going through a predictor predicting
h and then h feeds into the encoder of the decoder you can ignore this part for
now in the unconditional version you just have y that goes to an encoder
it produces a prediction for what the optimal value of the z variable is okay
called z bar and then the z variable itself goes into
the the decoder it goes you know it's being regularized as well and then
produces a reconstruction y bar and what you do here is again you find
the z value that minimizes uh the energy
um but what we're gonna uh but the energy now is uh is still the
sum of the two those two terms c of y y bar and r of z
but then what we're gonna do is we're gonna train the encoder
to predict this optimal value of z obtained through minimization and this
encoder is going to be trained by minimizing this uh
this term d of z and z bar so basically it views
z as a target value and you train it by back prop by
you know gradient descent to basically make a prediction that's as close to z
as possible okay that's one form of this idea
another form of this idea slightly more sophisticated
is that when you're doing the minimization with respect to z of the
energy with respect to z you take into account the fact that you
don't want z to get too far away from z bar so basically
your energy function now has three terms it has the reconstruction error it has
the regularization but it also has the difference between
the uh z bar the prediction from the encoder
and the current value of the z variable so the
energy function now is is written here E of x y z
is equal to the C function that compares y and the output of the
decoder applied to apply to z this is the unconditional
version here and then you have a second term which is
the this D function that sort of measures the distance between z and the
encoder applied to y there shouldn't be an x and
then you also regularize z okay so basically you're telling the
system find a value for the latent variable that reconstructs
that is sparse if R if is a is a L1 norm or doesn't isn't too uh
doesn't have too much information but also is not too far away from whatever
it is that the encoder predicted and a specific idea there is called
LISTA which means the Learning ISTA and is to shape the
architecture of the autoencoder so that it looks very much like a ISTA algorithm
so if we go back to the the ISTA algorithm
uh the formula uh the second last formula here um
you know looks like uh you know some vector update with a with some matrix so
it's like a linear stage of a neural net if you want
and then some non-linearity that happens to be a shrinkage which is sort of a
double value if you want it's when were you going up uh married with
another value going down and so if you look at the diagram of
this uh of this whole uh ISTA algorithm it looks like this
block diagram here that i've drawn on top you start with y
multiplied by some matrix and then shrink
the result then it gives you the next z apply some other matrix to it add it to
the previous value of z that you had shrink again and then
multiply the matrix again add to the previous value you had shrink
again et cetera and so you have two matrices here W(e) and S and
at the bottom if you define W(e) as 1 over L W(d)
and if you define s as the identity minus 1 over L W(d)
transpose W(d) where W(d) is the decoding matrix
then uh this diagram basically implements
uh ISTA okay so the idea that one of my firmware post docs Carl Greger
had was to say well why don't we why don't we treat this as a recurrent
neural net and why don't we train those matrices w
and S so as to give us a good approximation
of the optimus pass code as quickly as possible
okay so we're basically going to build our encoder network
with this architecture that is copied on ISTA
and we know for a fact that there is going to be a solution
uh where the system basically learns this the value
of W(e) and S that correspond to the the the one they should be um but in fact
the system learns something else okay so uh this is
another representation of it here at the bottom left we have the shrinkage
function and then this S matrix and then you add
the you know y multiplied by W(e) to the S
matrix shrink again et cetera et cetera so that this is the
recurrent net we're going to try we're going to train
with W(e) and S but the objective of this ISTA is
can you repeat what is the objective I think I missed the point
so the objective of training this uh encoder
okay so the the encoder in this in this diagram on the right here
the architecture of the encoder is the one you see at the bottom left
okay and the objective that you're training this with
is the average of D of z and z bar okay so the procedure is uh
in the case where there is no x right but if there is an x doesn't make much
difference so take a y for this particular y find the value of
z that minimizes the energy and the energy is the sum of
three terms C of y y bar R z and d or z z bar okay so find a z
that reconstructs um has minimal capacity but also is not
too far away from the output of the encoder
okay once you have the z compute the gradient
of the energy with respect to the weights of the decoder
of the encoder and the predictor if you have one
by backprop so the interesting thing is that
the only gradient you're going to get for the encoder is the gradient of D
of z and z bar okay so the encoder is just going to train itself to minimize
the z and z bar in other words it's going to
train itself to predict z as well as possible the optimal z that you
obtain through minimization the decoder is going to
train itself to uh of course reconstruct y as well as
well as it can with the z that is being given and then
if you have a predictor you're going to get gradient to the predictor and it's
going to try to kind of produce an h that you know helps as
well as possible is that clear? yeah, thanks
okay so that's the that's the architecture it's basically just a
pretty garden variety recurrent net and this works really well in the sense
that as you go through
you know the iterations of this uh ista algorithm
or this or or through this train neural net that is designed to
basically approximate this solution what you do is you um you can train the
system for example to produce the best possible solution
after three iterations only right so it knows the optimal value because
it's been completed with ISTA but then when you train it it it trains
itself to produce the best approximation of that value with only three iterations
and what we see is that after three iterations it produces a much much
better approximation than ISTA we produce in
three iterations and so what you see here is the number
as a function of number of iterations of either ISTA or this LISTA algorithm is
the reconstruction error right so by
training an encoder to kind of predict the result of the optimization you
actually get better result than if you actually run
the optimization for the same number of iterations
so the accelerates inference a lot okay so this is what spice coding
uh gives you uh with or without an encoder actually
uh you get pretty much the same results here when you train on MNIST so
these are um basically it's a linear decoder the
the code space here the z vector has size 256
and so you take this 256 vector multiplied by matrix and
and you reconstruct a digit and what you see here are the columns of
this matrix represented as images okay so each
column has the same dimension as an MNIST digit right
uh each column of W and so you can represent each of them as an image
and and these are the 256 uh columns of W and what you see is that
they basically represent parts of characters like little pieces
of strokes and the reason for this is that you can
basically reconstruct any character any in this digit
by a linear combination of a small number of those strokes
okay and so that's kind of beautiful because this system basically
finds constitutive parts of objects
uh in a completely unsupervised way and that's kind of what you want out of
unsupervised running you want sort of you know what other what other
components or the parts they can explain what my data looks like
um so this works really beautifully for uh for MNIST
uh it works quite nicely as well for uh natural image patches there's
supposed to be an animation here but you're not seeing it obviously because
it's pdf uh the result is this um so the
animation shows the learning algorithm taking place
so here again these are the the columns of the decoding matrix
of a sparse coding system with L1 regularization that has been trained on
natural image patches and I said that those natural image
patches have been uh whitened which means they've been sort of normalized in
some way you know cancel the mean and kind of normalize
the variants and you get a nice little
what's called Gabor filters so basically you know small edge detectors at various
orientations locations and sizes
so the reason why this was invented by neuroscientists is that
this looks very much like what you observe uh
in the primary area of the visual cortex when you
um when you poke electrodes in the visual cortex of
most animals and you figure out what patterns do they maximally respond to
they maximally respond to oriented edges this is also what you observe when you
train a convolutional net on imagenet the first layer features
look very much like this as well except they're convolutional these ones
are not convolutional it's it's trained on uh you know image patches but there
is no convolutions here so this is nice because what it tells
you is that with a very simple unsupervised learning algorithm we get
essentially qualitatively the same features that we would get
by you know training a large convolutional net supervised so that
gives you a hint so here is the convolutional version
so the convolutional version basically says you have an image
this is more responsive by the way what you're going to do is going to take
feature maps okay let's say here four but
it could be more and then you're gonna you're going to convolve each of those
feature map with uh with a kernel
okay so a feature map is I don't know let's call this
zk okay and we have a kernel here um
well let's call it Zi because i'm going to use K for the kernel
Ki and this is going to be a reconstruction y
and our reconstruction is simply going to be
the sum over i of Zi convolved
with Ki okay so this is different from the original sparse coding where
y bar was equal to the sum over columns of a column of
a W matrix so um and uh
multiplied by a coefficient Zi which is not a scalar
right so regular sparse coding um you have a weighted sum of columns
where the weights are scalar coefficients of Zi's
in convolutional sparse coding it's again a linear operation but
now the dictionary matrix is a bunch of convolutional kernels
and the latent variable is a bunch of feature maps
and you're doing a convolution of each feature map with
the each kernel and some of the results this is what you get so so here there
are um it's it's one of those system that has a
decoder and an encoder the encoder is very simple here it's basically
just a essentially a single layer network with a non-linearity and then
there is a simple layer after that basically a
diagonal layer after that to change the gains
but it's very very simple and the filters in the encoders and
the encoder and the decoder look very similar so it's basically the encoder is
just a convolution then some non-linearity I think it was
hyperbolic tangent in that case and then a basically what amounts to a
diagonal layer that just changed the scale and
then the decoder then there is a sparsity on the
constraint on the on the code and then the decoder is just
a convolutional linear decoder and the reconstruction is just a square
distance so if you impose that there is only one
filter the filter looks like the one at the top left is just a center
surround type filter if you allow two filters you get kind of
two weirdly shaped filters if you let four filters which is the
third row you get uh oriented edges horizontal and vertical
but you get two two polarities for each of the filters
for eight filters you get uh oriented edges at eight eight
different orientations 16 filters you get more orientations and
you also get center surround and then as you increase the number of
filters uh you get sort of more diverse uh filters not just uh
edge detectors but also grating detectors at various orientations center
surround etc and that's very interesting because
this is the kind of stuff you see in the visual cortex so again this is an
indication that you can learn really good features
in completely unsupervised way now here is the side news if you take those
features you plug them into a convolutional net
and you you trend that on some tasks you don't
necessarily get you know better results than you you
train on imagenet from scratch but there are a few instances where this
has helped boost the performance particularly in cases where the number
of label samples is not that great or the number of categories is small
and so by training purely supervised you get degenerate
uh uh features basically here's another example here uh same
thing um again it's a convolutional space coding
here the decoding kernel this is on color images
the the decoding kernels are uh nine by nine uh applied convolutionally
over an image and what you see on the left here are
the the sparse codes here you have um I don't know
64 uh feature maps uh and and you can see that the the z
vector is extremely sparse right there's only a few components here that are
either white or black or non-gray if you want
and it's because of because of sparsity okay uh in the last few minutes we'll
talk about uh variational autoencoder and I guess
you've heard a bit of this from uh tomorrow we're gonna be covering this
tomorrow with the bubbles and the code and everything right so
tomorrow is going to be one hour of just this. Right so um but here is
a preview for um how variational encoders work
okay so variational auto-encoder are basically the same architecture as the
one I showed previously uh so basically uh auto-encoder
ignore the the conditional part the part that's
conditioned upon x for now uh that could be a conditional version
of the auto-encoder but for now we're just going to have a regular version of the
encoder so it's an auto-encoder where uh
you take you know you take the variable y you run it to an encoder
uh it could be a multi-layer neural net convolutional net whatever you want it
it produces a prediction for the sparse code z bar
is a term in the energy function that measures the square this
the euclidean square euclidean distance between between z the latent variable
and z bar and there's also a
this is a this another cost function here which is the
l2 norm of z bar in fact generally it's more the autonomous z actually that
would be more more accurate but it doesn't make much
difference and then z goes through a decoder which
reconstructs y and that's your reconstruction error
okay now the difference with previous so this
looks very very similar to the type of autoencoder we just talked about
except there is no sparsity here and the reason there is no sparsity is because
variational encoders use another way of limiting the information content of the
code uh by basically making the code noisy
okay so um here is the idea
the way you you compute z is not by minimizing
the energy function with respect to z but by sampling z
randomly according to a distribution whose logarithm
is the the the cost that links it to z bar okay so
basically the encoder produces a z bar
and then there is an energy function that measures the the
distance if you want between z and z bar you think of this as the logarithm
of a probability distribution so if this distance is a square
euclidean distance what that means is that the
the distribution of z is going to be a conditional gaussian
where the mean is z bar okay so we're going to do is we're going to
sample a random value of z according to that distribution basically
a gaussian whose mean is z bar okay and that just means adding a bit of
gaussian noise to z bar that's what rz is going to be and you
run this to the the decoder so when you train a system
like this what the system wants to do is basically
make the z bar as large as possible make the z bar vectors as large as possible
so that the effect of the gaussian noise on z would be as small as possible
right relatively speaking if the variance of the
of the noise on z is one and you make the z bar vector
very very long like uh norm it doesn't uh then the importance of the noise
would be 1 % with respect to z okay so if you train
an auto encoder like this uh ignoring the fact that you had noise
by just back propagation uh what you'll get is uh z bar vectors
that get bigger and bigger the weights of the encoder will get bigger and
bigger and the z-bar vector will get bigger and
bigger so what's the trick in variational
autoencoder hold on, question uh quick question, where does this z come
from? Is that a latent variable never observed?
It's a latent variable that we are sampling and we're not minimizing with
respect to it so in previous cases we were minimizing
with respect to the z variable right minimizing the energy with respect to
the variable finding the z that minimizes
the sum of c uh D and R so here we're not minimizing
we're just we're sampling we're viewing the energy
as a distribution as a log of a distribution
and we're sampling z from that distribution. All right so imagine our
encoder produces the following points for training samples okay so these are
the z vector the z bar vectors produced by the encoder
[Music] um you know at some point
in training so what the effect of this uh sampling of z
is going to do is basically turn every single one of those
uh training samples into a fuzzy ball okay because uh we take a sample
we add noise to it and so basically we've turned
a single code vector into kind of a fuzzy ball
now the decoder needs to be able to reconstruct
uh the the input from whatever code is being fed and so if two
of those fuzzy ball uh intersect then there is some probability
for the decoder to get basically make a
mistake and confuse the two samples confuse one sample for the other
okay so the effect of training the the system if you if you
add fuzzy balls you know if you make every one of your code
a fuzzy ball is that those fuzzy balls are going to fly away from each other
and as I said before this is the same you know I was saying this before in a
different way it's going to make the weights of the encoder very large so
that the code vectors get very long and basically they get away from
from each other and the noise of those fuzzy balls don't matter anymore
okay so here if the fuzzy balls don't intersect
the system will be able to perfectly reconstruct every sample you throw at it
my question it was a couple of slides again but again on the same
topic it was a couple of slides ago so when you what exactly do you mean by
degenerate features here when you when you said that when you were comparing
self supervision and normal super completely supervision
I see okay uh that's a good question the what I was saying is
it's something I I said before in different turns it's the fact that if
you train uh a a classifier let's say
a convolutional net uh on a problem that has very few
categories let's say face detection you only have two categories the
representation of faces you get out of the convolutional net are very degenerate
in the sense that they don't represent every image
properly right they're going to kind of collapse a lot of different images into
sort of a common into identical representations
because the only thing the system needs to do is discriminate
from faces to you know faces with non-faces and so it
doesn't need to really kind of uh produce good representations of of
the entire space uh uh it just needs to tell you if it's
if it's a face or another face so for example the features you will get for
two different faces will probably be fairly identical so
so you don't so that's what I mean by degenerate features
what you want are features that basically
uh feature vectors that are different for different objects regardless of
whether you trained them to be different or not so if you
train on imagenet for example you have 1000 categories and
and so because you have a lot of categories you get features that are
fairly diverse and they cover a lot of the space of possible images
I mean they're still kind of fairly specialized but they're not completely
degenerate because you have many categories
and you have a lot of samples the more samples and more categories you have
the the better your features are in fact um
uh if you if you think about it an auto encoder
is a neural net in which every training sample is
is its own category right because you're basically telling the
system produce a different output for every sample I'll show you
so you're basically training a system to represent every object in a different
way but it can be degenerated another way
because the system can learn the identity function
and encode uh anything you want if you think about the Siamese net
the metric learning system the contrastive methods MoCo PIRL and
uh and SimCLR I was I was telling you about uh it's it's a little
bit of the same thing um they they they try to
learn non-degenerate features by by telling the system
you know here is two objects that I know are the same here are two objects that I
know are different and so make sure you produce different
feature vectors for objects that I know are
are semantically different okay that's kind of a way of
uh you know making sure you get you get feature feature vectors representations
are different for for things that are actually different
um but you don't get this by training a
conv net on a two-class problem or a 10-class problem
you need as many classes as you can afford
so pre-training using self-supervised learning basically
helps uh making the feature more more generic
and less less degenerate for the problem okay so let's get back to variational
twin colors so um so again if you train your auto encoder with
those fuzzy balls they're gonna fly away from each other
and what you want really is you want those fuzzy balls to basically kind of
cluster around some sort of data manifold right so you
want to actually keep them as close to each other as possible
and how can you do this you can do this by
essentially linking all of them to the origin with a spring
okay so basically the spring wants to bring all those points towards towards
the origin as close to each other to the origin as possible
and so in doing so what the system is going to try to do is pack
those fuzzy spheres as close to the origin as possible
and it's going to make them sort of overlap interpenetrate
but of course if they interpenetrate too much
if the two spheres for two very different uh samples
interpenetrate too much then those two samples are going to be confused
by the decoder and the reconstruction energy is going to get large
and so what the system ends up doing is only letting
two spheres overlap if the two samples are very similar
and so basically by doing this the system finds some sort of
you know representation of the manifold it puts the
the those those code vectors along uh a manifold if there is one
and that's the basic idea of uh variational of autoencoder now you can derive this
with math and it doesn't make anything much
you know easier to understand in fact it's much more abstract
but that's basically what it does in the end so there's a bit
uh there's a couple more tricks there um in that in that uh
in the variational of the autoencoder idea and you'll get some details uh with uh
Alfredo tomorrow um you can adapt the uh the size of those fuzzy balls
so basically you you can have the encoder compute the optimal size of the
balls in each direction and what you have to do is make sure
that the balls don't get too small and so
you put a penalty function that tries to make the
the variance of those balls uh the size in each dimension if you want
as close to one as possible they can get a bit smaller they can get larger if
they want but there's a cost for making making them
different from from one so now the the trick the the problem you
have with this is to adjust the relative importance
of the of this uh spring uh strength if the spring is too large is
the if the spring is too strong then the
fuzzy balls are all going to collapse in the center
and the system is not going to be able to reconstruct properly
if it's too uh weak then the fuzzy balls are going to fly away from each other
and the system is going to be able to reconstruct
everything and anything and so you have to strike a balance between the two and
that's kind of the the difficulty with variational
autocoder if you increase the strength of the spring a
little too much it's it's a term called KL divergence
in the in the in the system it's a KL divergence between
the gaussian basically of a gaussian it uh
it collapses okay um it you know all the fuzzy balls basically
get to the center and the system does not actually model it to that properly
I have a question uh about one of the previous lectures actually so
is that all right sure um yeah so when you were talking about
uh linearizability so generally when you were saying that stacking
linear layers one after the other without having non-linearities
is basically redundant because we can have one linear layer to do it
but I remember that you also mentioned there is one particular reason why you
might want to do this where you just stack
linear layers after this and you said well there's one reason but
you didn't go into that reason so i was wondering if there is anything
significant behind that uh so the situation I was describing
is that imagine you have uh you know some some big neural net
and it produces you know a feature vector of a certain size
and then your output is extremely large because
maybe you have many many categories maybe you're doing
a phonemes classification for a speech recognition system so
the number of categories here is uh you know 10 000 or something like that
okay I have to draw slowly so if your feature vector here is
itself something like like 10 000 the matrix to go from from here to here
will be 100 million right and that's probably a bit too much so
what people do is they say we're going to factorize
that matrix into the product of two skinny matrices
where the the middle dimension here is maybe
I don't know a thousand well you have you have
10k on the input 10k on the output and then the middle one
is 1k right so if you don't have the middle one
then the number of parameters you have is 10 to the 8.
if you do have the middle one is uh is 2 times
uh 10 to the you know seven okay so you you get a factor of of
10. if you make it 100 then it's you know 10
to the 6. so it becomes more manageable so basically you get a low rank
factorization so the overall matrices here that you
can call W is not going to be the the product of
two smaller matrices U and V
and because U and V uh the the middle dimension if you want
of U and V is smaller say 100 then the rank
of the corresponding matrix W would be smaller
there are people who do this without actually specifying the dimension
of the middle layer by doing what's called a minimization of nuclear norm
which is equivalent but uh I don't want to go into this but
that would be kind of a situation where you might want to actually
decompose a matrix into a product of two matrices to kind of save uh parameters
essentially your save computation um there's also another
uh interesting phenomenon which is that it turns out that
both learning and generalization actually are better
uh when you when you do this kind of factorization
even though the now the optimization with respect to this matrix becomes
non-convex it actually converges faster using
stochastic gradient there's a paper by a series of paper by
nadav if you're interested in this
Nadav Cohen I think he's from 2018
he's his co-author with Sanjiv uh Arora
from Princeton Nadav was uh a postdoc with Sanjiv Arora
and they had a series of papers on this um that explains why uh even linear
networks actually converge faster and they use it
also to um
to basically study the dynamics of learning uh in sort of non-convex
optimization as well as the the generalization properties
How important is it to have a kind of matching in a variational auto-encoder
how important is it to have a matching kind of architecture of an encoder and a
decoder there's no reason for the two
architectures to match it's very often the case that
decoding is much easier than encoding so if you take the example of sparse
coding which I talked about um the you know in sparse coding where
the encoder is one of those sort of listed type encoder the encoder is
actually quite complicated whereas the decoder is linear
okay uh this is kind of a special case because
the the code is high dimensional and sparse
and so high dimensional sparse codes uh you know any function of a
dimensional sparse code to any anywhere basically can be
is quasi-linear a one way to make a a function uh linear is to basically
represent this input variable in a in a high dimensional space using a
non-linear transformation we've talked about this we discussed you
know what were good features and good features
generally consist of sort of expanding the dimension uh of the
representation in a non-linear way and making this representation sparse
and the reason for this is that now you make your function linear so
you could very well have a very complex encoder and a very simple
decoder possibly a linear one as long as your
code is high dimensional now if you have a low dimensional code
so auto-encoder with the middle layer is very narrow
where the code layer is very narrow then it could become very complicated to do
the decoding it may become a very highly nonlinear
function now to do the decoding and so now you may need multiple layers
there's no reason again to think that the architecture of the
decoder should be similar to the architecture of the encoder
now there is you know there might be they might
okay that said there might actually be good reason for it
okay uh and in fact there are models that uh I haven't talked about
because they're not kind of proven but um which are called uh stacked
autoencoders where where basically you have this idea so um you essentially
have an auto encoder where you have a
reconstruction error I'm actually going to erase this and
make it look like the this you know the autoencoder that
we talked about where there is sort of a cost for making the the latent variable
here different from the output of the of the
encoder so this is a z bar and this is a z if you want okay
now that's auto-encoder drawn in a in a funny way so this is y
and this is y bar at the bottom now I can stack
another one of those guys on top okay now I'm going to have to call this
z1 and I'm going to call this z2
[Music] etc
okay this I'm going to call y bar and this I'm going to call y
now what's interesting about okay I'm going to call the bottom one x
now change name now if you took if you look at the
you ignore the right part of the system look at the left part
you go to y and that looks very much like a like a classical
recognizer where x is the input y bar is a prediction for
the output and y is the desired output and there's a cost function that
measures the difference between the two okay uh the other branch that goes from
y to x that's kind of like a decoder where y is
the code but then you have codes all the way in
the middle because it's kind of a stacked autoencoder right so
every pair of layer every pair of encoder decoder is kind of a little auto
encoder and you kind of stack them on top of
each other and what you'd like is find a way of training the system in
such a way that if you don't have a label for samples
you don't you don't know why for the for example you just train this
as an auto encoder but if you do have a y then you you you
clamp uh y to its desired value and then this
system becomes now a combination of predictor a recognizer
and an autoencoder now there is a slight problem with this
picture this a number of different problems the first
problem is that if again if z1 for example has enough
capacity uh and you only train on unlabeled
samples the system is only going to carry the information through z1 and
it's going to just completely ignore the top layers
because there's not enough capacity in z1 to do the perfect reconstruction
so it's going to uh you know just put all the information to z1 and
then all the others z2 and y will be constant
because the system won't need won't need them so again you will need to
regularize to regularize z to prevent it from
capturing all the information and same for the other layers perhaps
now the other thing is uh would you know do this thing need to be
linear non-linear and that depends on the relative size of the
various z's so if you go from low dimension to high dimension
you need something that's non-linear but if you go from high dimension to low
dimension you can probably do it with a linear
kind of like sparse coding um and so you will see that the system
may have uh you know an alternation
of linear and nonlinear stages in sort of opposite phase if you
want because you need linear to go from high
dimension to low dimension and then nonlinear to go from low
dimension to high dimension and then again linear to go back to low
dimension it's the opposite the other way around
this is you know people have been proposing things like this but not
really sort of training them on a large scale
so there's a lot of sort of open questions around those things
uh one if you're curious one paper that I've
I've worked on with my former student uh called uh Jake Zhao
um is a system called stacked what where
auto encoder and it's a system a bit of this type but
there is sort of extra variables kind of going
this way which are basically the position of
switches in pooling I don't want to go into details but
if you look for a paper about stack where auto-encoders you'll find two paper
one by Jake and myself and a follower paper by a
group from Michigan university of Michigan that
basically uh enhanced it and sort of trained them on imagenet and got some
decent results so those are kind of architectures you can use to do kind of
self-supervised learning just to clarify the parameters for the
spring is for the KL divergence term in the loss
right yeah so the KL divergence uh term in the
in the loss we're gonna see this tomorrow guys so
uh we're gonna be going through the equation and all these uh
details so it's right I cover this tomorrow so I'll see you tomorrow
hopefully with the video as well uh if the
bandwidth supports it I will put this like this uh the
recording of this uh class online as soon as is actually
available to me I will add it to the NYU streaming
platform and then you know I will try to clean it
up as I can and you know upload it as well
on youtube later on all right so thank you again um stay
home stay warm and I see you tomorrow stay safe bye stay safe